Guide to the Barbara Bergmann Papers, 1942-2015 RL.11388
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Barbara Bergmann papers
1942-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bergmann, Barbara R.
RL.11388
13.5 Linear Feet
Barbara Bergmann was leader in feminist economics and author of 11 books. Her archival collection consists of published writings, including congressional testimony; assorted research files and projects, including a selection of books from her library; and personal miscellany, including some career awards.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into series: Writings, Research/Library Files, Project Files, Autobiographical/Personal Materials, and Teaching.
Biographical / Historical
Barbara Rose (Berman) Bergmann (1927-2015) was a leading feminist economist and author of 11 books. She was a professor of economics at University of Maryland and American University and served as president of the International Association for Feminist Economics, the American Association of University Professors, and the Eastern Economic Association.
Originally from New York City, Bergmann attended Cornell University and majored in mathematics, graduating in 1948 and taking a job with the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics. She earned a PhD from Harvard University in 1959, focusing on microsimulations of economic theories. She served on the President's Council of Economic Advisors during the Kennedy administration, and later advised both the Congressional Budget Office and the U.S. Census Bureau. She and her husband, Fred Bergmann, had two children, David and Sarah.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, except original audiovisual and electronic records are closed. Contact Research Services in advance to request the production of use copies of these materials.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Barbara Bergmann Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2017.
Collection Overview
The Barbara Bergmann Papers consist of writings by Bergmann, largely published versions, as well as some draft materials, project files, and research materials she accummulated. The contents of the collection speak to the breadth of Bergmann's interests in economic approaches -- including mathematical modelling, microsimulation, and government regulations -- as well as her wide ranging interests in sex and race discrimination, child care, poverty, affirmative action, economic aspects of parenting, education, domestic labor, wage discrimination, social security, and numerous other topics within the broad definition of feminist economics.
The Writings Series predominantly consists of publications -- essays, articles, chapters, and books -- authored by Bergmann. There are also copies of her testimonies to Congress on poverty and child care. Materials are filed by title, and any supplemental information (including research, correspondence, and drafts) are included with the final published version of the work. There are a wide range of publications represented in this series, including newspapers, academic journals, commercial presses, and academic presses.
The Project Files Series contains files from some of Bergmann's ongoing professional work, including a substantial amount of research and anecdotal evidence collected about marriage, intended for an unfinished book on the decline of marriage in America. The Project Files series also contains materials about Bergmann's economic activism, relating to her work identifying gender discrimination practices by Giant Foods, Inc., and her consulting role for the Service Employees International Union representing nurses in an anti-trust lawsuit against hospital salary practices in the 2000s.
A selection of published works collected by Bergmann on topics relevant to her research interests, including several Census Bureau reports, is held in the Research Files/Bergmann's Library Series. The Teaching Series includes course packs and hiring information from Bergmann's tenure in the American University Economics Department. Finally, the Autobiographical/Personal Materials Series contains some of Bergmann's awards and honors, including her B.A. from Cornell University; numerous interviews and statements from Bergmann discussing her career, personal history, and economic philosophy; and professional photographs of Bergmann.
Home economics -- United States -- History; Economics -- Statistical methods; Economics -- Periodicals; Feminist economics; Marriage -- United States; Discrimination in employment -- United States; Race discrimination -- Economic aspects; Sex discrimination in employment -- United States; Motherhood -- Economic aspects; Social security; Poverty -- Mathematical models; Income distribution; Affirmative action programs -- United States -- Management; Child care -- United States; Becker, Gary S. (Gary Stanley), 1930-2014; University of Maryland, College Park; American Association of University Professors; American University (Washington, D.C.) -- History; United States. Bureau of the Census; International Association for Feminist Economics; Dignitas (Organization); American Academy of Political and Social Science
- Writings, 1966-2015; 1
  - Essays, Articles, Reports, and Chapters, 1971-2014 and undated
    - The 1973 Report of the President's Council of Economic Advisors: The economic role of women, 1973 Sept. (Box 1)
    - Abolish the Nobel Prize for Economics, 1999 Mar./Apr. (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Published in Challenge Magazine
    - Alternative measures of structural unemployment, 1965 (Box 1)
      Published in Brookings Institution
    - Assessing the impact of alternative economic outcomes on social objectives, 1972 (Box 1)
      Chapter in Input-Output Techniques, ed. by A. Brody and A.P. Carter
    - Basic income grants or the welfare state: which promotes gender equality?, 2008 Dec. (Box 1)
    - Becker's theory of the family: preposterous conclusions, 1995 (Box 1)
      Published in Challenge Magazine and Feminist Economics journal.
    - Bloated administration, blighted campuses, 1991 Nov. Dec. (Box 1)
      Academe
    - Book reviews by Bergmann, 1984-2010 (Box 1)
    - A budget-based definition of poverty, 1993 (Box 1)
      Published in Journal of Human Resources
    - A business showcases its segregated staff, 1997 (Box 1)
      Published in Dollars and Sense
    - Changes in family and work roles of women and men: The challenge of policy, 1983 Oct. 27 (Box 1)
      Testimony before the Joint Economic Committee, U.S. Congress
    - Child care: the key to ending child poverty, 1996 (Box 1)
      Chapter in Social Policies for Children, ed. by I. Garfinkel, J. L. Hochschild, and S. McLanahan
    - Child support awards: state guidelines versus public opinion, 1995 (Box 1)
      Published in Family Law Quarterly
    - Combining microsimulation and regression: a "prepared" regression of poverty incidence on unemployment and growth, 1973 (Box 1)
      Published in Econometrica
    - Combining microsimulation and regression: a reply, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Comment on Higgin's "Women in the Islamic Republic of Iran: Legal, Social, and Ideological Changes", 1987 (Box 1)
      Published in Signs
    - The common sense of affirmative action, 1985 (Box 1)
      Chapter in Selected Affirmative Action Topics in Employment and Business Set-Asides
    - "Comparable worth" for professors, 1985 (Box 1)
      Published in Academe
    - The continuing need for affirmative action, 1999 (Box 1)
      Published in The Quarterly Review of Economics and Finance
    - The corporation faces issues of race and gender, 1996 (Box 1)
      Chapter in The American Corporation Today, ed. by C. Kaysen
    - A "cost-sharing" formula for child support payments, undated (Box 1)
      manuscript draft
    - Could Social Security go broke?, 2008 (Box 1)
      Chapter in The Economists' Voice, ed. by J. Stiglitz, A. Edlin, and J. B. DeLong
    - Curing child poverty in the United States, undated (Box 1)
    - The current state of economics: needs lots of work, 2005 (Box 1)
      Published in Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science
    - A debate on the budget deficit, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Debt-servicing in sanction-free situations: A comment, 1965 (Box 1)
      Published in The National Banking Review
    - Debt and taxes, 2000 (Box 1)
      Published in American Prospect
    - Decent child care at decent wages, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Deciding who's poor, 2000 Mar./Apr. (Box 1)
    - Diagnosing discrimination, 1976 (Box 1)
      Chapter in Equal Employment Opportunity and the AT&T Case, ed. by Phyllis Wallace
    - Discrimination (Dictionary entry), undated (Box 2)
    - Discrimination and unemployment, 1980 (Box 2)
      Chapter in Unemployment in Western Countries, published conference proceedings for International Economic Association
    - Discrimination through the economist's eye, 2008 (Box 2)
      Chapter in Sex Discrimination in the Workplace, ed. by F. Crosby, M. Stockdale, and S. A. Ropp
    - Do sports really make money for the university?, 1988, 1991 (Box 2)
      Two versions, published in Footnotes (AAUP) and Academe
    - Does the market for women's labor need fixing?, 1989 Winter (Box 2)
      Published in Journal of Economic Perspectives
    - Economic issues in child care policy, 1994 Dec. (Box 2)
      Published in Pediatrics
    - Economic risks of being a housewife, 1981 May (Box 2)
      Chapter in Women and the Economy: A Reader, ed. by E. Mutari and D. Figart
    - Economic support of "fatherless" children, 1981 (Box 2)
      Chapter in Income Support: Conceptual and Policy Issues, ed. by P. Brown, C. Johnson, and P. Vernier
    - Economics of women's liberation, 1973 Mar. (Box 2)
      Published in Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences
    - The economy and the economics profession: both need work, 2008-2009 (Box 2)
      Published in Eastern Economic Journal
    - The effect of wives' labor force participation on inequality in the distribution of family income, 1980 (Box 2)
    - The effect of white incomes of discrimination in employment, 1971 Mar./Apr. (Box 2)
      Published in Journal of Political Economy
    - Empirical work on the labor market: is there any alternative to regression running?, undated (Box 2)
      Published in Econometrics
    - Equality in retirement benefits: the need for pension reform, 1975 Fall (Box 2)
      Published in Civil Rights Digest
    - Evaluating and forecasting progress in racial integration and employment, 1972 Apr. (Box 2)
      Published in Industrial and Labor Relations Review
    - An experiment on the formation of expectations, 1986, 1988 (Box 2)
      Published in Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization
    - Feminism and economics, 1983 Sept./Oct. (Box 2)
    - French child welfare system: an excellent system we could adapt and afford, 1993 (Box 2)
      Chapter in Sociology and the Public Agenda, ed. by W. J. Wilson
    - A fresh start on welfare reform, 1987 (Box 2)
    - The future of child care, 1995 Aug. (Box 2)
      drafts
    - Gender in public expenditure reviews, 2005 (Box 2)
      Chapter in Public Expenditure Analysis, ed. by Anwar Shah
    - Government support for families with children in the United States and France, 1996, 1997 (Box 2)
      Published in Feminist Economics
    - Have economists failed?, 1974, 1975 (Box 2)
      Proceedings and conference issue, Eastern Economic Journal
    - Helping working parents is key to reducing child poverty in America, 1997 (Box 2)
      Published by National Center for Children in Poverty
    - The housewife and social security reform: a feminist perspective, 1982 (Box 2)
      Chapter in A Challenge to Social Security, ed. by R. Burkhauser and K. Holden
    - How to analyze the fairness of faculty women's salaries on your own campus, 1975 (Box 2)
      Published in AAUP Bulletin
    - The immigration controversy we should be having, undated (Box 3)
      Draft
    - In defense of affirmative action, 2000 (Box 3)
      Chapter in Sex, Race, and Merit, ed. by F. Crosby and C. VanDeVeer
    - Income for the single parent: child support, work, and welfare, 1987 (Box 3)
      Chapter in Gender in the Workplace, ed. by C. Brown and J. Pechman
    - Instead of "Cut 'Em Off": a program to help working parents, 1995 May (Box 3)
      Published in The Nation
    - Is affirmative action a quota system?, 1997 (Box 3)
      Chapter in Civil Rights and Race Relation in the Post Reagan-Bush Era, ed. by Samuel Myers, Jr.
    - Is there a conflict between racial justice and women's liberation?, 1985 Summer (Box 3)
      Published in Rutgers Law Review
    - Job bias is still the rule, not the exception, 1995 Mar. 22 (Box 3)
      Published in Newsday
    - Los Angles Times editorials, articles, 1983-1988 (Box 3)
      Various clippings and articles written by Bergmann.
    - Labor market data needs relating to anti-discrimination activity, 1979 Apr. (Box 3)
      Published by National Commission Employment/Unemployment Statistics
    - Labor market failures in nursing, 2006 Nov./Dec. (Box 3)
    - Letters to the editor, 1980s-2010s (Box 3)
      Various published letters to the editor, written by Bergmann, collected from assorted newspapers and journals.
    - Loose pages of unidentified drafts, undated (Box 3)
    - Lone mothers: what is to be done?, 2004 Jul. (Box 3)
    - Long leaves, child well-being, and gender equality, 2008 (Box 3)
      Published in Politics and Society
    - Macroeconomic effects of a Humphrey-Hawkins type program, 1977 (Box 3)
      Published in American Economics Association
    - Macroeconomic models on microfoundations: data requirements, 1984 (Box 3)
      Published in Review of Public Data Use
    - Making child care "affordable" in the United States, 1999 May (Box 3)
      Two versions, published in The Annals: Silent Crisis in U.S. Child Care (special issue) and Social Politics
    - Marriage in America / Ever after, 2007 Jun. (Box 3)
      Times Literary Supplement book reviews
    - "Measurement" or finding things out in economics, 1987 Spring (Box 3)
      Published in Journal of Economic Education
    - Micro-simulation: models, methods, and applications, 1980 (Box 3)
      IUI Conference reports (3 articles)
    - Micro-to-macro simulation: a primer with a labor market example, 1990 Winter (Box 3)
    - A microsimulated model of inventories in interfirm competition, 1990 (Box 3)
    - A microsimulation of the macroeconomy with explicitly represented money flows, 1974 (Box 3)
      Published in Annals of Economic and Social Measurement
    - Needed: a new empiricism, 2007 Mar. (Box 3)
      Published in Economists' Voice
    - New directions for poverty research, 1978 (Box 3)
    - New hope for welfare reform, undated (Box 3)
    - New York Times Economic Affairs Forum columns, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
      Photocopies of Bergmann's columns
    - The nurse shortage is a crime, 2006 Nov./Dec. (Box 3)
    - Occupational segregation, wages, and profits when employers discriminate by race or sex, 1974 Apr./Jul. (Box 3)
    - The occupational standing of Negroes by areas and industries, 1971 Fall (Box 3)
    - The only ticket to equality: total androgyny, male style, 1998 (Box 3)
      Published in Journal of Contemporary Legal Issues
    - Pay equity: how to argue back, 1985 Nov. (Box 3)
      Published in Ms. Magazine
    - Pay equity: surprising answers to hard questions, 1987 May/Jun. (Box 3)
    - Policy explorations with the transactions model of the U.S. economy, 1980 (Box 3)
      Chapter in Microeconomic Simulation Models for Public Policy Analysis, Vol. 2, ed. by R. Haveman and K. Hollenback
    - Political economy of the deficit, undated (Box 3)
      Roundtable transcript page proofs
    - Probing the opposition to affirmative action, 1995 Apr. (Box 3)
      Published in Gender, Work, and Organization
    - Prospect of equality of incomes between White and Black families under varying rates of unemployment: a comment, 1972 Fall (Box 3)
    - Is prosperity possible without growth?, 2010 Sept./Oct. (Box 3)
    - The provision of adequate, equitable, and assured economic support for children, 1981 Apr. (Box 3)
      Draft proposal for a study
    - Pushing for a more humane society, 2004 (Box 4)
      Autobiographical, published in The American Economist and in Reflections of Eminent Economists
    - Real welfare reform: help for working parents, 1996 Sept./Oct. (Box 4)
    - Reducing inequality: merit goods versus income grants, 2006 Winter (Box 4)
      Published in Dissent
    - Reducing the pervasiveness of discrimination, 1976 (Box 4)
      Chapter in Jobs for Americans, ed. by Eli Ginzberg
    - Reducing poverty among American children through a "Help for Working Parents" program, 1997 Nov. (Box 4)
      Foundation for Child Development working paper
    - Remedies for occupational segregation by sex in the U.S., 1997 (Box 4)
      Chapter in Occupation Segregation of Women Workers in Japan, Philippines, and the United States
    - Setting appropriate levels of child-support payments, undated (Box 4)
      Proofs
    - The share of women and men in the economic support of children, 1981 May (Box 4)
      Published in Human Rights Quarterly
    - The shibboleth of the shrinking pie, 1981 (Box 4)
      Published in Perspectives
    - "Signing up the littlest": universal pre-K, 2002 May 12 (Box 4)
      Published in Boston Sunday Globe
    - Social relations in the workplace and employer discrimination, undated (Box 4)
      Published in IRRA 33rd Annual Proceedings: Equal Opportunity
    - Social security and the interests of women, 1979 Jul. 24 (Box 4)
      Testimony before the Task Force on Social Security and Women, Select Committee on Aging, U.S. House of Representatives
    - Social security disaster myth, 2012 Jul. 29 (Box 4)
      Published in Philadelphia Inquirer
    - Software as a public good, 1993 Oct. (Box 4)
      Published in Viewpoint
    - Spreading the misery faster as a strategy for controlling inflation, undated (Box 4)
      Incomplete draft, with edits.
    - Statement: Economic report of the President, 1981 Jan. 28 (Box 4)
      Hearings before the Joint Economic Committee, Congress of the U.S.
    - Statement: Economic status of women, 1982 Feb. 3 (Box 4)
      Hearing before the Joint Economic Committee, Congress of the U.S.
    - Statement: Economics of sex discrimination in employment, 1973 Jul. 10 (Box 4)
    - Statement on "Fair Insurance Practices Act" (S.2204), 1982 Jul. 15 (Box 4)
      Senate Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation
    - The struggle of women in the U.S., 1974 Aug. (Box 4)
      Published by UN Association of Sweden
    - Student teaching evaluations: inaccurate, demeaning, misused, 2003 Sept./Oct. (Box 4)
    - Subsidizing child care by mothers at home, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
      Two versions: Foundation for Child Development, Feminist Economics
    - A Swedish-style welfare state or basic income: which should have priority?, 2004 (Box 4)
      Two versions: Chapter in Redesigning Distribution, ed. by Erik Olin Wright, and article in Politics and Society journal
    - Testimony in support of HB1021: Death with Dignity, undated (Box 4)
    - Thinking about child care policy, 2002 (Box 4)
      Chapter in The Economics of Work and Family, ed. By J. Kimmel and E. Hoffman
    - Towards more useful modes of research on discrimination in employment and pay, 1974 (Box 4)
      Published in Sloan Management Review
    - Two cheers for CSWEP?, 1998 Fall (Box 4)
    - Two notes on working wives and family income inequality, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Unemployment rate targets and anti-inflation policy as more women enter the workforce, 1978 (Box 4)
      Published by American Economic Association
    - The United States of America, 1985 (Box 4)
      Chapter in Women Workers in Fifteen Countries: Essays in Honor of Alice Hansen Cook, ed. by Jennie Farley
    - What the common economic arguments against comparable worth are worth, 1989 (Box 4)
      Published in Journal of Social Issues
    - What to do about single parenthood, 2014 and undated (Box 4)
      Huffinton Post blog draft
    - What would we gain by subsidizing child care?, 2004 (Box 4)
      Chapter in Squaring Up, ed. by Mary King
    - Why do most economists know so little about the economy?, 1989 (Box 4)
      Chapter in Unconventional Wisdom: Essays on Economics in Honor of John Kennedy Galbraith
    - Women's interests in pension reform, 1979 Nov. 30 (Box 4)
      Testimony delivered to the President's Commission on Pension Policy
    - Women's roles in the economy: teaching the issues, 1987 Fall (Box 4)
      Published in Women's Studies Quarterly
    - A workable family policy, 1988 Winter (Box 4)
  - Books by Bergmann, 1966-2005
    - America's child care problem: the way out, 2002-2003; 3 folders (Box 6)
      Written with Suzanne Helburn. Copies of the book, reviews, marketing.
    - Decline of marriage and what to do about it, undated (Box 6)
      Chapter 1 draft, with edits. Additional materials for this book are in the Project Files series.
    - In defense of affirmative action, 1996 (Box 6)
      Copy of book, reviews.
    - The economic emergence of women, 1986 (Box 6)
      Copy of book, marketing, reviews.
    - The economic emergence of women, 2005 (Box 6)
      Copies of second edition.
    - The impact of highway investment on development, 1966 (Box 6)
      Written with G. Wilson, L. Hirsch, and M. Klein. Copy of book.
    - Issues in contemporary economics: women's work in the world economy, 1992 (Box 6)
      Edited by Bergmann; copy of book.
    - A microsimulated transactions model of the United States economy, 1986 (Box 6)
      Written with R. Bennett. Copy of the book, reviews.
    - Saving our children from poverty: what the United States can learn from France, 1996-1998 (Box 6)
    - Is Social Security broke?, 2000, undated (Box 6)
      Drafts, proofs, copy of the book, reviews and press coverage.
- Project Files, 1972-2013; 2
  - Bellagio residency, Rockefeller Foundation, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Press clippings re: Bergmann, 1975-1985 (Box 6)
  - Jen Cohen project (topic unknown), correspondence, 2013 (Box 6)
  - Dignitas, 2010s (Box 6)
  - Economists' Policy Group for Women's Issues press release, 1995 (Box 6)
  - French-American Foundation Child Care Study Panel report: A Welcome for Every Child, 1989 (Box 6)
    Bergmann served on the study panel.
  - Giant Food Inc./Economic Equity Group research, correspondence, and survey, 1972-1995; 2 folders (Box 6)
    Research and other materials investigating hiring of women as managers/supervisors by Giant Foods, Inc.
  - Higher education costs, 1990s (Box 7)
    Research/reports re: college costs
  - Economic models programming (unknown project), 1990s; 5 folders (Box 7)
    Incond, Simula, Tdata, Pretsr, and Regres. Text file printouts.
  - Economic models programming disks (unknown project), 1990s; 6 disks; Disks are of unknown type and undocumented creation and use. Any data present on the disks are inaccessible as of January 2019. (Box 5)
    Economic models electronic media (3.5" floppies) for unknown programming project.
  - Marriage research files, 2010s; 16 folders (Box 7)